Hello, hello, Paweł Malik, Portal Analiz. It is a pleasure for me to welcome today the representatives of the company Sanex,
i.e. Mr. Romuald Kaliciak and Mr. Marc Kosman. Hello, gentlemen.
Sanex is definitely one of the stars of last year. At the beginning of last year, I will remind you, we had a webinar with the current gentlemen from the office.
At that time, it was a very optimistic attitude, but with some concerns about the costs, in particular the costs of steel.
However, it turned out that this year was phenomenal and probably exceeded your expectations. I think we will hear that for sure.
However, of course, what interests us most is not only history, but also the future, which can be expected in the upcoming 2023.
I think the environment will benefit, as the gentlemen have prepared for it. I give you my voice. I know that there will be a presentation at the beginning.
After the presentation, there will be time to ask questions. You can already enter the questions in the chat, which I will read out at the end of the presentation.
So, once again, Mr. Witam, I give you my voice. Thank you very much.
We have prepared a short presentation here to make it easier to ask questions and show our company what has changed this year, that year, actually.
And show a few directions or proposals for the development of our company in the coming years, in particular this year.
So, one by one, first of all, such basic information about the company for those of you who may not know us yet, but would like to better understand what the company is doing.
Then a short presentation of the financial results for the last year.
Then information about the market, where we sell, to whom we sell, on which markets, to whom we would like to sell and a overview of the most important events that have been happening in our company for the last year.
So, as we have already been presented, we will try today with Mr. Mark, who is our member of the financial detector management and, in my opinion, to present in such a way that everyone will be able to draw from it the information that we intend.
So, let's start with the company. The company has a lot of experience in relation to all products and all technologies that have been used since the very beginning of the renewable energy industry.
We have an experience of 20 years, as it was shown here, although the company started in 1997 as a different subject in this industry.
Here we show our company, as if in such a basement, as it was shown here, that is, we show a large range of our products, we show future directions, such as fruit, we show the results that have grown very nicely for us here in that year, so we would like to focus on this now, in particular.
What are we specializing in here? Our company, from my point of view, is mistakenly, every time it is encrypted into some parts of this large range of renewable energy products.
So at the beginning it was that we were encrypted into solar generators, which were considered products that no longer sell, later there were photovoltaics, which, due to the lack of funding, also stopped selling.
Now there are heat pumps that can play a big role, or not, so we have to see that this is a product that is largely dependent on the level of funding and the price of energy.
We produce a whole range, i.e. here, regardless of which product or which product range would be at the top, so to speak, this is how it is produced here.
So we produce a whole range of heat pumps, a whole range of solar, flat, or vacuum collectors, we produce power systems for photovoltaics, we finish the construction of the hall, we already produce in a very large number of containers, we produce glycol, we produce various chemical products that are used to clean or fill solar installations,
or to install heat pump cleaners. We produce controllers, we produce heat accumulators on the basis of phase cross-section of the solar panel, so here we have the whole range.
Here we show our experience in research and development activities. Every company that wants to play an innovative role or take part in the construction of the energy and wind energy market, from my point of view, should have a very well-developed research and development department.
The development department is the place of the company that decides on the directions that should be examined, it should introduce certain products, certain technological thoughts that could be transferred to the construction or creation of products that would be sold.
And it has given us the need to sell the whole system, not only the individual elements of the system, but also the whole system.
And as a confirmation, our research and development department works quite vigorously. These are donations that we received from companies for innovative solutions, there are quite a few, I think, especially we are proud of this autonomous heating system,
because it is a program that we are doing with the National Development Fund, a research program, and it shows our ability to create new, technologically advanced solutions and later commercialization of these solutions and operations of these clients.
Our company also has a number of different certificates that allow our products, both for heating and solar collectors, first of all, to be allowed to be sold on the Western European market and also allows the participation, funding for final customers of these devices.
This indicates that these devices are highly efficient and economical. Yesterday we managed to extend the ISO 9000 certificate for the entire company.
Now we would like to show you some financial data, because it is certainly very interesting. It's nice that we have a research and development department, that everything is developing, but all of this has to be converted into financial results later.
And indeed, here we have a comparison after three quarters, how much we have managed to improve profitability, i.e. these fears that the growth of the cost of raw materials, in general, the cost of activities last year, we managed to keep all these costs in our pockets.
And if we have an increase in revenues at the level of over 100%, then we have an increase in profitability at the level of 270%.
So you can see that this additional developed margin has been very nicely converted into financial results for our profits. These are, of course, data after three quarters, full financial data annually, because they will be published more in a month.
We also invite you to get acquainted with this. For sure, there will be no negative surprises at the end of the year, this trend will be maintained until the end of the year.
Here you can see nicely on the charts how we have grown in the last year, when it comes to revenues, and here are the annual revenues, because we have already shown them to the public, and net profit after three quarters of the year 2022, we have a significant increase in profits in 2021.
It can be said that we have managed to improve revenues very much this year and at the same time maintain the costs of activities, first of all, the costs of a few raw materials, and the personal costs of raw materials.
Now we will move on to the information about the market, who are we selling to, who would we like to sell to, what does it look like?
Well, if the financial results presented here were excellent, then the product that we have produced should be found by the buyer.
Here we can see that our main market, which is the German market and the Polish market, are different.
However, we would like to change this a little bit.
On this slide we show which are the key countries for us in the discussion.
We see Germany, Austria, Italy, Germany and a few other countries that we will try to satisfy in a greater way, as well as expand the countries that are not yet the appropriate colors on this map.
These are the new countries, such as France, Spain or England, where these products are very popular.
Here we show our two main countries, where we are trying to exist to a greater extent, which are Germany and Austria.
Austria, through the purchase of a company that deals with assembly, which is a large company in Austria, which is known and recognized on the Austrian market, has been on the Austrian market for over 100 years.
And in Germany, we are trying to develop a company in its own range, according to our own plans and projects, which we consider to be the right ones for the German market.
Now we would like to bring you closer, from our point of view, to the most important events that have had an impact on the activities of our companies in the last 12 months.
In the last few years, we have been operating as a foreign company, but now we have decided to create a company, a company, a capital company in Germany.
For this reason, in order to sell more technologically complex devices such as heat pumps to customers in Germany, the trust of the client must be built and there must be a service in place.
German customers, rather technological things, want to buy a company that is registered and located in Germany. At the moment, we are already working quite intensively on the creation of an assembly team in Germany, on the production of individual, final customers for heat pumps.
In the last year, since the establishment of such an information company, we have already managed to make 2 million euros of income, so at the beginning we are satisfied.
Another very important thing for us is that we managed to get the permission to create a special economic zone on one of the sections for which we invest and build a new hall.
Since we managed to achieve a nice profitability, our profits are large, so the impact of this fiscal burden is also quite large.
Thanks to this, we will be able to do some of the activities related to the production of the assembly element for the heat pump, which will be carried out in the area of the zone.
Here, too, significant fiscal savings can be made.
We have just completed the construction of a new hall in the area of this zone. At the moment, production lines are installed for assembly units, for photovoltaics, for thermal collectors.
More or less the first test production is in June-July, while on a full scale from the end of the year, according to the plan, the new factory line will begin to function in this hall.
We decided on a slightly different direction of development in Austria, i.e. we did not create companies from scratch. We were looking for a ready-made company that would be acceptable.
We found a very interesting company with a long history as a company that used to be in the construction of heating, then in the construction of basements, and for some time it was also very much engaged in the installation of OZ solutions, heat pumps, photovoltaic installations.
On the basis of this company, we want to manage the entire Austrian market, i.e. also develop the hot trade in this country, the internet trade.
This company made an income of less than 20 million euros last year. As a result of consolidation, it will be visible at the end of the year, because the company came in January at the end of the year, it will not be consolidated yet.
However, as a result of the consolidation at the end of the year, it is certainly a significant development step for our company.
These are the most important things that we wanted to present to you, and now, if you are interested in our presentation, we invite you to ask questions.
Thank you very much for the presentation. Of course, I encourage you to ask questions, the first ones have already appeared.
However, before I start reading them, I have a few questions of my own. First of all, an incredibly high increase in income in 2022, really full recognition. What were the reasons for such a dynamic growth?
There was certainly not just one reason, but many. According to me, we were able to quickly assess the market properly.
That is, we assessed the market that it will simply have income, it will be able to sell, it will have goods.
We also talked about the fact that all the possibilities of delivery, storage and price uncertainty, a lot of companies just got scared.
They did not order the right amount of the right products, they were unable to produce their product, and they could not sell it.
The company that could produce, it also took advantage of it in two ways.
First, it could sell its products, and secondly, due to the fact that these products were lacking on the market, at the same time, it looked like the margin was a little higher than normally with standard sales, where after each year you have to fight and make significant offers and competitors.
According to me, this is a good analysis of the market and preparation of a hub for such a difficult time.
Are these factors, because I understand that they disappeared a bit, those that were beneficial, i.e. the lack of goods on the market, currently you are working in such an environment that this product is there.
Therefore, can you expect an increase in sales or will this year be more difficult?
The year will be much, much more difficult, not only for us, but also for the whole world, according to me.
I think that due to the fact that inflation is high, credit rates are also high, it is difficult to get a credit that you could think of, it is a cheap credit that you can afford.
Therefore, the number of investments will definitely decrease. If the number of investments decreases, the number of purchased goods will not be the same, i.e. the competitiveness of these companies will have to be greater.
Last year, he sold the one he had and was able to use it. Today, there will be a battle on the other side.
Theoretically, the Polish market is already being signaled that it is not a market that is growing or that is behaving evenly, but it is a market, unfortunately, that is getting better.
So here again, according to me, we have a good chance, because we are on different markets with our products.
Last year, we managed to invest a lot of money so that we would be on the German market to a greater extent and on the Austrian market to a greater extent on other European markets.
We managed to make additional certificates on the heat pump. All the markets in the European Union are markets that are state-owned, that defend the access to these goods.
It is not as easy as it is in Poland. In Poland, any company can buy any product and introduce it to the market from our industry without any restrictions or problems.
Austrian or French markets are markets where it is very difficult to sell our product in Poland. Unfortunately, you have to have the appropriate certificates of a given country, permits.
These markets are protected by the policy and by the government of a given country. We don't have that.
That's why we needed that year. It was a very nice year, because we managed to get on the lists of products that are funded in Austria and Germany and build this experience that will allow us to sell our products on these markets, I think, with the success of our country.
It sounded a bit unoptimistically that this year would be difficult, but your plans are to increase these revenues and gain growth. Is it still a difficult business?
Yes, it is still a difficult business. Our plans are always comprehensive. I think that the market and economy will be difficult this year.
The same thing was very difficult for us that year, but it was perfect for us. That's why, on the one hand, I'm talking about the market and economy that awaits us.
I don't think that we will be the ones who will not be able to use it to their advantage. We think that this year we will be able to show our positive sides and win in these situations and in the economy that we will be in.
I think it will be a positive year.
Well, a bit of optimism has appeared. How did the sales structure look last year? What part was the export?
Last year, almost 70% were sold on foreign markets, mainly on the German market.
This year, I suspect that the export will increase even more after the adoption of the Austrian company. When will the Austrian company be fully consolidated?
The first consolidated result will be after the first quarter on March 31st. There is one more thing to note here.
The Austrian company had a moving turnover year, which started in March and ended in February.
The turnover year for the Austrian company will start in March and end in February.
But the consolidation will be from the moment of adoption?
The consolidation will be from the moment of adoption, i.e. we will consolidate the results from February 1st.
We will show consolidated results, i.e. the first consolidated report with the Austrian company will be at the end of the first quarter.
Do you want to sell your products in Austria under the brand of this company or introduce the Sannex brand?
For us, it is the expansion of our sales opportunities.
We will certainly sell and expand the assortment of products sold under the brand Kovac.
We will also supply and lead the sales of our products to very large recipients and producers as Sannex.
Please tell us about the structure of sales from the point of view of products.
You have the whole range of these products.
As you mentioned, you are first associated with collectors, with photovoltaics, now there are heat pumps.
What does this sales structure look like when it comes to products?
Fortunately, it is perfect.
All products that are associated with renewable energy and with the thermal part of this industry are produced by us.
We produce control systems with these complicated devices and entire systems, as well as each component of this system.
We produce heat pumps in a fairly large range, from 3 kilowatts to 35 kilowatts of power.
We produce solar collectors, we produce containers, we produce mounting systems.
Therefore, the assortment of products that we produce allows us to increase the European market very smoothly.
They are not everywhere to finance.
In one country they are like that, in another one they are like that.
We can also adjust from this large range of products what people want to buy in a given country,
because the government allows them to partially finance the purchase of these products.
Therefore, we can sell as much as possible on each market.
This is logical, but we can also adjust.
Our products are distributed to different markets.
In Germany, other heat pumps are sold than those in Poland.
We are different.
We have different systems that are required in the German market so that we can sell them.
The assortments have to be different, so that they can be configured with heat pumps and photovoltaics, so that they can be sold.
We have adapted products for each market.
The parts that sell well are financed.
But how is your sales dependent on a particular group of products?
Does it depend on the majority of sales or a certain number compared to another group of products?
Yes, it is.
In different periods of time in our company, different products are higher.
In larger quantities, they sell in smaller quantities.
For example, in recent years, products related to photovoltaics were very popular.
These products related to photovoltaics are still produced in large quantities, despite the fact that few people in Poland talk about photovoltaics,
because this preferential way of financing has ended.
But in Europe, these products are still well-stocked and are a large part of our production.
It is not always what is fashionable in Poland that we produce in large quantities.
Rather, we look at it globally and, according to European needs, we try to adapt to production.
Therefore, we are also developing production possibilities, for example, with photovoltaic mounting systems.
The entire hall that is being prepared, well, actually not the whole hall, of course, but it is very large,
will serve to develop the production possibilities of mounting systems related to photovoltaics.
How have the production capacities changed after the launch of these lines in the new hall?
Theoretically, the line is prepared for a new type of mounting system.
We have long tried to introduce other types of mounting systems into HENEC,
which are characterized by a lower use of materials and better durability.
For example, in Austria, there is a lot of snow on the roofs and those systems must be able to function,
even with such heavy rains, 1-2 meters of snow, they must function.
In addition, we have some ideas that have been with us for a few years,
and this type of machine that we have ordered will enable the production of such mounting systems.
Therefore, on the one hand, the production possibilities will increase,
which is certainly an interesting thing, almost 60-70%,
but a very innovative product will also be created, which will be launched today.
Do you predict that there will be a full use of these production powers by the end of the year,
i.e. there will be a request for these new products and what will be produced in this hall?
If we knew that, it would be cool.
We assume that, according to the talks that we have conducted,
we were now at the exhibition in Frankfurt,
we could meet with our clients and also with new companies that are willing to cooperate.
Therefore, I believe that the mounting systems that are sold today are characterized by a high cost.
There, the durability of certain elements is based on the thickness of the steel.
We believe that this is not a good road because the trucks are shaking.
I believe that it is possible to do much better with a well-designed hook.
You can save material, but you need appropriate machines.
Therefore, we believe that if we use less raw materials and make a much better element,
I think that we will have a very interesting product and it will be of great interest to us.
Okay, let's move on to the questions that have already appeared a bit.
I will present them one by one, as long as there are no answers to them.
I think we will jump a bit when it comes to areas.
Let's start with something that we haven't talked about yet.
What are the issues regarding the work on Vodor?
Does the company run such work at all?
Vodor is behind us, years ago there were two such directions.
It was geothermal and water.
So Vodor a few years ago was a very difficult topic
because very few companies in Europe had research opportunities
regarding the use of Vodor in OZ.
Vodor was used in the automotive industry, as well as in other industries, but not in OZ.
Today, we are still collecting experience,
we are still studying the possibilities of using how Vodor could be used
for heating systems, for storing energy.
It seems that the biggest disadvantage of photovoltaics for me
is the inability to store electricity for a long period of time.
We are talking about two weeks, months, two months, three months.
Here, storing electricity for such a long period of time is not possible
because of financial or technical reasons,
because a standard storage of energy is 10 kilowatts, 23 kilowatts,
and that's too much money because every 10 kilowatts is about 10 thousand euros.
We can accept that.
We believe that Vodor would be a perfect material
that can store this energy for a long period of time.
And in this direction, actually, our gaining experience
on what we should pay attention to, what it should look like.
We are very, very, very far away
so that we can say that this system should look like this or that or that.
So we are preparing for various competitions here,
which I hope will eventually be presented,
and then with these ideas we will try to get into the field of these companies
that will show the possibilities of storing and using Vodor
and producing Vodor from renewable sources of energy,
including photovoltaics,
and storing it for a longer period of time
and using it at the moment when we will need this energy,
whether it concerns single-family homes
or larger buildings or applications in transport itself,
in production or on site.
In my opinion, it will be possible to use this Vodor
in the place where it was created.
And through photovoltaics,
that is, through the use of something that does not burden the natural environment.
This direction is very, very relevant and interesting to us.
What dynamics of the company's arrival are expected in the coming years?
This is a very difficult question,
because on the one hand, the OZE solution market is in Poland
and in Poland it is not an independent company.
In European countries it is very dependent on legal solutions
and financing that the governments of their citizens offer us.
On the other hand, for sure,
dynamic increases of 100% annually,
the more and the bigger the company has its arrival,
the more difficult it is to achieve such large growth levels.
Therefore, it is difficult to expect that growth
can be maintained at a level of 100% for a few years.
However, we would like it to be such above-standard increases,
which companies set somewhere 10-20%.
This is maybe a bit ambitious for us.
However, growth above 100% is again not very realistic.
But this year, for sure, the company will add quite an important amount of money.
Yes, of course, if such one-time events such as the purchase of a company,
they automatically allow us to double the turnover in consolidated results.
Therefore, the question is what plans for this year?
Are you still preparing some admissions?
We are still looking at the European market
for subjects that would fit our production,
our products and our activities.
We are still looking at the things that would be part of our responsibility,
whether it is sales, production or such a living element.
We are currently analyzing companies that are on sale in our industry,
in Germany or Switzerland.
This would be a potentially interesting direction for us.
Can we expect any new year this year?
No, we are not able to say right now.
At the moment, we do not have a company chosen
that could enter the game.
We are at the stage of market observation.
Something interesting can be shown all the time.
At the moment, however, there are no talks with anyone.
However, this does not exclude the fact that in two or three months
an interesting offer will appear and such talks will begin.
We are open to this.
They can also agree quickly.
Even now, when we say that we have nothing planned,
in a month it may turn out that in two months we will be in the game.
This may also happen.
We are still checking the market to see what interesting things will happen.
The economic situation may also affect the appearance of new offers
or the absence of new offers.
The situation is very dynamic and will continue.
Therefore, I think that we are well prepared to control the market
and see what is happening.
One of the elements of this strategy is also the willingness
to make potential decisions.
Who is the competitor for Sanex?
The competitor for Sanex in terms of products
are certainly a few European companies,
maybe two or three,
which have a very high potential in the products they produce,
i.e. they produce a large range of products.
There are certainly such companies,
because we will not talk about them,
but they are such.
In Poland, rather due to the assortment we produce
and in terms of quantity, we do not have competition.
There are companies that produce a similar range,
but in a very modest assortment and quantity.
What is the competitive advantage of the company?
Our company has the biggest competitive advantage
due to the assortment.
We have seen several times that due to the assortment of products
that we produce for a very large assortment,
it allows us to survive very well
those periods that are worse in Europe or Poland.
If a product is believed to no longer be sold,
and the sun collector,
then we have, first of all,
because we are in different countries,
it already allows us to sell this collector in larger quantities,
as well as even if we sold it less,
because then other products appear,
e.g. photovoltaics,
which is sold in larger quantities.
Therefore, one product that compensates for the potential
losses that could happen on this collector.
Therefore, from my perspective,
I think that the biggest point of attention
is the assortment of very innovative products.
Our products, we come out of the education of the poor.
We have always produced a lot of different products for someone.
And that limited us.
We were not able to force the introduction of innovative production methods.
We simply had to produce on order,
as our clients wish.
If we sell our brand,
we have been selling our brand and our products for a few years,
we have very innovative products in the assortment.
We have products that are not yet sold today.
We have such products.
These are all hybrid systems.
These systems, despite the fact that they sound cool
and everyone thinks they are interesting,
it is not yet time for these systems.
Here, the signal has to be received by developer companies,
by construction companies, by installation companies.
They have to get used to different standards.
We have such products.
We are prepared to offer such products.
We show them.
We train installers.
We show what the advantages of these products are.
I think this is the second member that distinguishes us.
We do not produce the same product all the time
and we simply sell it until it becomes fashionable
and stops being sold,
but each of our products,
due to the very large research and development department,
is developed in terms of innovation,
in terms of production methods
and in terms of using this product at hand.
Each of our products can cooperate,
change products and create very complicated systems.
I think that the direction of development in the European market
is to operate entire systems
that cooperate with each other,
are intelligent and can be controlled and managed
in such an economic way.
Here the question and fear comes back,
whether it is possible to treat the year 2023,
I think it is about the previous year, 22,
as a one-off,
and now there is a return to the normalization of sales
in the following years.
Were these margins in 2022, however,
higher than what can be expected in the coming years?
Yes and no.
As we said, that year was definitely a unique year
for many companies.
Some companies ceased to exist,
and other companies grew.
This is the state that was well prepared
and did not have a hard core like a tree
and was flexible and could not prepare for it and wanted to.
This win, who did not do it, lost.
This year will be exactly the same.
The one who does not prepare well for these changes
that are economic changes in the year,
and in Poland they are visible,
this one will not go through it.
You have to aggressively try to start working
and prepare for the new reality
that surrounds us and will not be interesting.
So these are negative things in relation to the economy,
but positive in relation to us.
We believe that we have products prepared for this
and we can win in this economic situation.
Today we are fighting to be part of a large company
in the field of renewable energy,
but measured in European standards, not Polish.
That is why we believe that every investment
as it will be in this year,
should allow us to get to this level faster,
to the level of these big companies
that can operate in the European market as a whole.
That is, they can offer their solutions as a whole,
i.e. such systems.
I believe that it will be a good year.
The year will be bad for the economy for the state,
and good for us.
What are the predictions for the growth of sales
in relation to Mój Prąd 5.0 in Poland?
Are you still focusing on exports to Germany and Austria?
Yes, we are focusing on exports to Germany and Austria.
I will tell you why.
Because we are all talking about 5.0 in the new program,
but to this day no one knows what the program will be like.
There is no deadline yet.
This morning I checked, there is no deadline for the 5.0 program yet.
So there are assumptions, there are predictions, as always.
We introduce a program in Poland,
and this program is 100% prepared for people,
end users,
i.e. the end user does not play a role.
He will be glad that such a program has been created,
because he can use it.
But please note that these programs are not consulted,
they are not prepared with companies that are supposed to take part in it.
This is only half of the matter.
If we knew that we would need energy warehouses in a year,
Polish companies, Polish entrepreneurs
could produce such warehouses, take part,
build the second part of this economy.
Production companies would hire people,
people would buy products,
companies would buy products,
co-products would produce all the products
that this end user could buy.
This is only half of the matter.
We will probably find out in this day,
when the program will enter life or the day before,
what will be financed and what will happen.
Every company that wants to make money
will have to buy it somewhere outside,
or be lucky and buy it in Poland,
because it will turn out that someone has it.
After all, it is a bit illogical.
In the end, in Poland, in terms of production,
it would be very, very unfair
to our employees and to our workers.
We would never know in our lives
how much money is intended for this.
When they finish, it would be impossible to plan.
Production companies have to plan on a scale of two years,
minimum.
A year is waiting for ordering a machine.
If we do not know what kind of product
will be financed, how are we supposed to produce it,
how will we wait for the machine?
This does not work.
Therefore, the main security of production opportunities,
as well as the implementation of new products,
are foreign countries.
They guarantee the continued sale of our products.
And whether we get to pin 0 or 6.0 in Poland,
we will see.
But whether it will be the whole system,
whether it will be half of the system,
whether we will be able to produce it, we do not know.
A year ago there were quite a few concerns
about the costs, in particular, how much steel has grown.
The situation on the steel market has changed,
it is positive, I think, for companies.
However, other costs are growing, energy, gas,
rewards. How does it look for you?
We are trying to take into account
things that are obvious.
It was obvious last year
that the costs and logistics of delivery,
delivery chains, that they would be difficult.
We took it into account,
we managed to predict some market situations
and react well to them.
Today we know for sure that energy costs
will not be drastically cheaper.
Rather, they will be the same or more expensive.
Maybe they will not be as expensive as everyone expects,
but they will definitely be more expensive.
These are things that are stable.
If we know these things that will probably happen,
we can react to them and prepare for it.
That is, either negotiate materials,
use others, negotiate prices
or construct a technological process
in such a way that it uses less energy.
We can use photovoltaic panels
to use the amount of current that is used
to create it ourselves.
We take advantage of all these possibilities.
We try to present to each of these possibilities
the consequences of what will happen
in order to prepare for them.
It is clear that we are able to
negotiate with all the consequences,
but if someone is already thinking about this topic,
we can predict certain things
that will probably happen.
I think that we are being prepared
by a good company for such difficult times
to avoid all the unfortunate situations
that will arise.
I think that this way will not be interesting.
Therefore, it requires again
the use of certain visualizations
of possible events
and trying to avoid them.
Do you have energy prices
secured in any way
or do you buy it on a regular basis?
We have energy prices secured
at the level of the previous year,
so if there were any drastic moves
in this year,
it should not touch us.
Do you provide an emission of shares
in order to finance further investments?
It is always an open topic
in the open market.
If, for example,
an interesting large company appears,
we will consider such a step.
However, at the moment,
we either implement these current investments
with our own funds or with bank financing.
However, if a large investment
appears on the horizon,
we will consider it an open issue.
After all, these are companies on the stock market,
so as to provide some financial development
and income from the capital market.
We also have to consider
that the price of our companies
is very, very, very, very, very low.
From my point of view,
a quick decision
on some emissions and such things
theoretically does not exist.
I believe that we are very, very undervalued
because we are not yet a very recognizable brand
in Poland,
but in Europe more.
First, we should work on the high value
of our company.
I think that one share is already undervalued on the stock market.
Of course, questions are also being asked about the price.
Despite the continuous development of the company,
excellent results from the financial report
of the Sannex shares fell from PLN 30 to 20.
Are you able to explain this logically?
No, and I am.
I believe that we should not have any positive ...
We have been making positive announcements for the last five years.
All in turn, every quarter better,
100%, 200%.
I think this is a mistake.
We should not say anything, then it will probably be okay.
When we look at companies from our industry,
everyone has a problem.
One has millions, millions, millions,
more credits than profits,
it almost stopped functioning, something else,
and everyone has a nice price, much higher.
And we have Sannex, positive announcements,
and we do not have a price.
Of course, there is such a correctness.
After every positive announcement, the shares fall.
I'm afraid it will be the end of the quarter, it will be a tragedy.
Okay, so there will be good quarter results.
How are the shares supposed to fall?
Okay, the second question.
I understand that you feel that this is a big undervaluing,
that you have ambitions to be a company at the European level
and appreciated by this prism
to beat the next European markets,
and not only by the prism of Polish photovoltaics,
as many people qualify you.
Great.
Okay, now the question is about the funds in the other direction.
Can you say something about the dividends this year?
I mean, there will definitely be dividends this year.
How much exactly will it be,
we are still conducting analyzes here,
how much money we will need for investment,
how much we can afford to pay,
such analyzes are going on, there will definitely be.
It will probably be closer to the annual level,
maybe a little higher.
Well, from our perspective, as we always say,
we wanted to be a company for a few years,
we are a company of the Domona dividend.
For today,
from the perspective of pricing
or the friendliness of the market,
looking at us, I mean, it does not have much influence.
So, but we stay with the assumptions
that we made at the beginning.
The question is about the shares,
newly acquired, what are the economic plans,
construction plans, their destination
and when are the investments planned for them?
Investments in the shares are scheduled
all the time, so here we have
for a few years there is no period
that investments should be conducted.
Investments are either very large,
very large amounts that consume a lot of energy
or those that end or start.
So the shares that the company has managed to buy
are conducted all the time.
These houses are renovated,
they are prepared for their goals
that we have there.
Every year, theoretically,
we have some new big investment
that we give away or some house that we need
to produce or store.
These investments, probably from my point of view,
I've been sitting here for a long time
as a president and I think
I have more experience than one client.
We build all the time, and all the time it is too little.
So there is no way that I will say,
oh, now we will finish and then we will not build for two years,
we will probably be even more.
Investments are conducted all the time,
it also requires the robotization
of the industry of our production processes.
We are implementing very innovative
production processes,
it was necessary to show later
a larger majority.
If we produce something where normally
in the industry, for example, 100 welders
we have three robots
that do it automatically,
maybe this investment is expensive at the beginning,
maybe it is difficult because it requires other people
to handle these things, to program, to supervise,
then in the final effect,
with greater production and so on, it shows
that it was a very good decision and it pays off
to make this decision.
How do Western companies achieve higher margins than in Poland?
Well, yes,
to put it bluntly,
generally, yes,
because, after all, the market in Poland is still cheaper,
which is competitive
in relation to the West.
However, with standard products
that are produced in large quantities,
then you have to sweat a lot
to be able to offer products and have nice clients
and deliver to the market.
This is how it looks,
depending on the product, but in principle,
the market as a producer in Poland,
compared to the Polish market,
the market may be bigger.
There is such a question that I would also like to ask
after a few years of product sales,
the target base of customers will be huge,
and in the company great know-how.
It would be possible to offer high-margin services
on your own various products, I understand probably
some warranty services or something additional,
but my question is more on the other side.
Who is your client? Is it a physical person
who decides on a given product?
Who really is the main client?
Difficult question,
because in Poland our client is the municipality,
we are very large,
we do municipal sales,
we have a municipality client,
we have a lot of montages made,
we have a final client,
even if we sell through distributors,
our client is the final client
who would, for example,
expect a service or an operational review
or other things.
So here we lead a very large part
of our activities to this day.
There are such activities as
offering a disc,
this disc was our name,
before this disc,
a well-known disc,
remains with this disc,
which offers security
in relation to the extended warranty
of the 24-hour service.
So here all these additional components,
in addition to sales themselves,
begin to play a big role.
We try to resummulate
and properly divide
and guarantee this final client
or this municipality
or this foreign client
or company the appropriate range of action.
It's not that simple,
because in Germany there is something else
expected, in Austria something else,
so we try and believe
that this aspect
and type of activity
will continue to gain
the appropriate range of action in a few years.
I would just like to add
that our Austrian company,
which we have bought, has already achieved
a fairly large share of income
in terms of service and warranty services.
They have a larger percentage share
than we try to achieve,
so maybe we'll take a look at them a little bit
as to who is organized,
but there you have already managed to do it.
We were talking about foreign acquisitions,
we were talking about departments that you have,
which you invest in, and are new investments in the country planned
rather not.
Rather not, because of the super cool frame
that we have,
I think we have our good results
and all our successes,
which in the first place are the responsibilities
of our people.
We have these people here,
our employees have been working for many years,
we have a very nice frame,
everyone is involved,
so here is our great victory
that we have such a team and not another.
This is our common success,
so I think we shouldn't invest in other places
because it would be difficult to build such a team
and such a management in a short period of time,
so we will rather try to keep
our production going
in the long run.
If we are already talking about employees,
what model of change work is currently being carried out?
Three changes.
So there is a lot of work.
Yes, there is a lot of work, so we are working on three changes
or two changes, depending on the product,
A question about liabilities.
The liabilities from the delivery title
increased to 51 million from 16.5 at the end of 2021.
How many pre-determined liabilities were there?
I was the first one, it was over 30%,
and does one client dominate there?
At the moment, we do not have any pre-determined
and longer liabilities, of course,
a few three or four days a week is the standard,
we do not have any risk,
all these liabilities from large clients are secured,
we do not see such a risk,
we have also normalized the way of calculating
with our associated companies,
so we do not see any risk there.
The question is, if you are developing so quickly,
do you have any problems with the staff in the Polish market?
Are you looking for specialists?
Yes, this is the biggest problem
when it comes to dynamic development.
If the company develops at a pace of 20%,
then there would be no problem,
because the staff is like us on a regular basis,
so we are very engaged in employing people
after school, after practice,
and after all possible directions,
if you want to come to us to work,
to try to make it possible,
as much as possible,
when crossing a certain speed of development
it is difficult, because not all employees
want to advance so quickly,
maybe it's funny, but that's how it is,
some people feel good in this work
and in the positions they are,
and looking for people who will help us in this fast development
is really a big problem for us,
and we are looking all the time,
maybe it looks funny,
all the time we are looking for at least 10-20 people
only to manage different processes
or to manage different aspects of social activities.
What percentage of sales generates the largest customers?
I think no more than 25%.
I would like to ask about the negotiations
about which there was talk.
We are talking about the Polish Ecology of Negotiations.
How does the development of an independent company look like?
Do you acquire more such negotiations
from the municipalities?
What does the market look like for this type of services?
Surprisingly good.
I thought that this period was difficult
in that year,
because organising negotiations
always took many months,
so municipalities, when they had prices,
theoretically they had to make negotiations
that were no longer relevant in terms of prices,
because these prices grew much faster
than the pace of organising these negotiations.
However, we managed
to finish the year positively.
We finished this year positively
before the Polish Ecology of Negotiations,
and this year looks much better.
I mean, the prices of negotiations
are more realistic,
we have won a lot of negotiations,
and I think that 3-5 months in advance
we have already organised what and where we will edit,
in terms of quality.
We are well prepared.
In general, the assumption of negotiations
was that there would be a second sales leg in Poland,
in case there were some restrictions
on what we see now.
It is very good for us that we have in Poland
a second sales leg,
where the funds are not for individual clients,
who have less and less of it,
but those who still have access
to external European financing.
We hope that this access will be even greater.
These losses are possible
for individual clients.
Thank you for your time
and the willingness to meet with investors,
of whom there are nearly 100 online,
and probably more will watch it later.
There was a question on the chat
whether there is a chance for open days for investors.
Yes, for now we have parking lots
with cars that come for goods.
I was looking at it recently,
and I thought that it would be nice
to do something like that.
We do not have huge parking lots,
but all of them are parked with cars
that are waiting for goods.
It is a very nice idea,
and I think that time would be right
to do something like that,
because it would give a lot.
The hour has passed quickly.
Thank you very much.
I understand that you have ambitions
that are not local,
but European when it comes to sales.
We have to look at you as those
who deliver goods to these developed markets,
Germany, now Austria,
where it is very difficult for others to enter
the market.
I understand that you are very dissatisfied
with the current exchange rates,
but I think that through the results
you will prove that it is worth investing in you.
Thank you very much.
Goodbye.